Hello, and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going to
be exploring the different properties of
molecular compounds, specifically looking
at how intermolecular forces affect them.
So in this video, the whole idea of
what we're going to be trying to try to
keep in mind is intermolecular forces
are all about attraction, meaning that
all these different covalent molecules,
they have different electronegativity
that's assigned to every single atom.
So when we have a polar bond, Uh,
we want, that helps us be able
to recognize do we have a polar
molecule, which is really important.
So it's, I would recommend it's really
important to try to memorize some of
these little trends for yourself, where
if something is nonpolar, typically it's
something bound to the same element.
So like your diatomic molecules or
something like C, H bound together.
So an organic chemistry, typically
when we see carbon to carbon, carbon
to hydrogen, these are nonpolar.
Now, when we are looking for polar
interactions, typically what we look
for is everything that's in like the
top right part of the periodic table.
So stuff like oxygen,
nitrogen, fluorine, chlorine.
If you see any of those atoms that are
bound to, let's say, carbon, typically
they are considered to be electronegative,
meaning that most likely they are polar.
Now this isn't all the time, right?
Those are polar bonds, but that
differs from a polar molecule.
So when we talk about polar, well,
molecules are polar when bonds work
together, meaning that essentially,
if you can kind of imagine it's like a
tug of war, there are going to be more
electrons kind of piled on, let's say
one side of a molecule versus another.
So if I were to look at
like nonpolar molecules.
Typically what happens is you have the,
the different pooling is canceling out.
So if I have like a linear molecule where
if you imagine you're playing tug of war
against your twin and you're both pooling
in opposite directions, so here we have,
uh, B, the B element on both sides is
both pooling, it's going to cancel out.
Now these are typically what we refer
to as our basic geometries, so things
like trigonal planar, tetrahedral,
if it's the same element on all the
different positions connected around
the central atom, they will all
cancel out, and that's stuff that
we've learned in previous videos.
Can it cancel?
That's the most important part.
Um, so generally we always see
that nonpolar, they have to all
be symmetric and the same atom.
So those are very important.
Same atom and symmetric.
Say that, just say that again, right?
So in order for it to be polar, there
has to be some kind of net dipole.
across the molecule.
Meaning that we have an uneven
sharing of electrons within it.
So if I have a lone pair, this is
generally a really good way to see
that we have this uneven nature.
Lone pairs are very electronegative,
so you'll see that all of it is
more gauged in one area, so it's
bent and trigonal in the middle.
So if you see a lone pair, generally
it's considered to be polar.
Now is that the only picture that we see?
Well, when it comes to symmetry, so
when an atom is not symmetric, it is
always polar, so keep that in mind.
So here I have a linear example where
we see the same atom again, right,
both pulling in opposite directions.
So this is nonpolar.
The second I replace one of them with a
different atom where it's different, It
could be more on one side or the other.
It's unbalanced, which is the important
thing that we're trying to visualize here.
So when we have this uneven sharing that's
here, this is when we create a dipole
that we can see within the molecule.
So we have the delta negative, the delta
plus, and what they're going to be doing
with one another is if you have multiple
molecules of the similar type, so polar
and polar, they will attract each other.
So when this happens, the properties
of different compounds will change.
So this is how we can make
homogeneous mixtures, uh, from
this, um, this complete mixing.
So this is where like dissolves
like, this phrase that I've
used before comes into play.
Non polar do not mix with
polar and vice versa.
They need to be the same type of property.
So we're going to take a look at this.
We're going to try to understand
what this whole entire polar molecule
idea is all about, so that way
we can kind of better understand
exactly what this thing looks like.
So in this video, we're going to be
really focusing on intermolecular
forces, meaning that when we have this
attraction between the polar compounds,
the polar and polar, Or non polar and
non polar, they will be attracted.
So, now keep in mind, these
are not actual bonds that are
forming, it's an attraction.
So the analogy I like to use for this all
the time is, think of it as, it's kind
of like your family versus your friends.
Intermolecular forces are like your
friends, you hang out with them, you talk
to them, you text them on a regular basis.
You can come with, you, you hang out with
them all the time, however, eventually
you both go home to your own houses.
Bonding, like covalent ionic, is like your
family, you're related through blood, you
probably live together, you're together
all the time outside of your normal life.
So, bonds hold together molecules,
they are very, very difficult to
break, which is really important.
Intermolecular forces are considered
weaker, but, and they can be broken very
easily, but they do affect the chemistry.
Quite a bit.
Now, where exactly does that play?
Well, it has to do with trying to see, uh,
thinking of gases, liquids, and solids.
So when you have all these different
substances, depending on how strong the
force is, is going to play a massive
role in how these things can fall
apart, how they can actually be seen.
So here I have a video that's being
shown, and this is one that we
can actually Get an idea of this.
So looking at the overall picture
here, we have two molecules
that are being heated up.
One's on the right hand
side, one's on the left.
The left is a strong intermolecular
force, which you see the temperatures
going up really quickly for both.
On the right hand side we have a very weak
force, so nonpolar versus polar molecules.
Now as they're heating, you'll see that
it takes a lot of heat for the polar
molecules to eventually break apart
and to fall apart, whereas nonpolar,
you heat it up, you still see it's
still in the negative degrees before
it goes from a solid to a liquid.
So it takes more energy, more heat, to
actually break apart all these molecules
that go from a solid to a liquid to a gas.
And this has to do with
the intermolecular forces.
On the left I have water,
which is hydrogen bonding.
On the right I have oxygen gas,
which is dispersion forces.
There's a massive difference between
these two different forces and
how they actually interact, right?
So hydrogen bonding is
a very strong force.
It takes a lot of time before it can
actually break apart into the gas phase.
So typically things that have very
strong interactions is what when
we find Uh, that they are typically
as a solid versus, let's say,
if I have a liquid, for example.
Solids and liquids have strong
interactions, whereas gases
typically are very, very weak.
Um, and it's kind of like the idea,
it's, it's very difficult for them
to want to leave those phases.
They want to interact with their friends.
They want to stay around with them.
So we're going to take a look at this
world and try to get an idea of how we
can actually understand the different
types of intermolecular forces.
Looking at the four different types of
intermolecular forces, the one thing we
have to realize is what exactly are they?
So we have ion dipole, hydrogen bonding,
uh, dipole dipole, and dispersion forces.
Now, when we are looking at each of these,
well, we go from strongest to weakest.
So, let's first start off
with ion dipole forces.
So, ion dipole, what that's all about
is that this is an electrostatic force
between an ion and a polar molecule.
So, when we have something like this,
well, where exactly can we find them?
This is whenever, like I said,
you have that ionic compound
mixing with a polar molecule.
So whenever this is happening,
it's generally whenever we try
to throw, let's say, an ionic
compound, like in water, for example.
And what it's going to do is the
water is going to completely surround
it and rip it apart into its ions.
So like, for example, you throw salt in
water, you can taste that salty taste.
What you're tasting is Na plus
and Cl minus, the ions that are
interacting with your taste buds.
So this is actually an
example of how that works.
Now this is your strongest force because
it can actually destroy an ionic bond.
Now, hydrogen bonding, on the
other hand, is whenever you have
hydrogen and it's covalently bound
to oxygen, nitrogen, or fluorine.
It has to be bound to one of those.
So whenever we have that interaction,
it is interacting with another
polar atom when it occurs.
So we always have HF, HO, HN,
when the hydrogen interacts
with a electronegative atom.
So let's say if I have like H2O and NH3,
they can hydrogen bond with one another.
There has to be a polar atom and then
one of them has to have a hydrogen on
it and it has to be directly connected
to oxygen, nitrogen, or chlorine.
Dipole dipole, on the other hand,
is whenever you have a positive
and a negative end for your polar
molecule, meaning that it's,
you know, opposite its track.
So whenever we are trying to show that,
we always have the two poles and we'll
draw little dots to illustrate that
we have that intermolecular force of
them actually talking to each other.
So this is whenever we have
polar molecules, when this is
occurring, we have the negative end
interacting with the positive end.
And just to kind of finish our
little mini review of all these
forces, dispersion is the last one.
This is a temporary attraction,
and this is going to be the
focus, a huge focus of this video.
This is how whenever we have dispersion,
this is a temporary shift of interaction,
meaning that the electron cloud that's
around these molecules will move, it
will, it will change, it will alter.
And now when that does, this can happen
in all molecules this can occur in.
However, this is the only force and
the strongest one for non polar.
But keep in mind, everything does it, but
it's the strongest force for non polar.
So when we are looking at all these,
right, and say all molecules, right,
we want to go from like right to
left when it comes to the strength.
So dispersion is your weakest, ion
dipole is your strongest force, and
it has to do with how more, how much
polar, how much more polar can you
possibly be when you're trying to
look at all these different forces.
So with the four intermolecular forces,
the thing that you're really going to see
that sets them all apart by looking at
them all is the fact that when you are
going from one to another, is that it's
the word dipole that makes them different.
Dispersion forces are nonpolar,
meaning they do not have a net dipole,
essentially it's been cancelled
out, right, due to the geometry.
Now, with dipole dipole hydrogen bonding
ion dipole, they have that unevenness
between from the electron cloud.
So when that occurs, they can interact
with one another to create all these
different forces and change their
properties and our understanding of them.
And that's what we're going to look
into is in part two, we're going to
understand how dispersion forces and
polarizability and the fact how these
things can interact with each other
and how it has an effect on like things
like melting point, boiling point,
and all these other different forces.
Let's take a look in our future video.